RG 005:028, Office of the Governor: Robert A. Hurley (1941-1943)
Connecticut State Library
Robert A. Hurley records
1941-1943
Connecticut State Library
Connecticut. Governor (1941-1943: Hurley)
7.75 cubic feet
Gov. Robert A. Hurley's correspondence and subject files.
RG005_028
Multiple
Biographical Note
Born: August 25, 1895 at Bridgeport, Connecticut.
College: Lehigh University.
Political Party: Democrat.
Offices: Governor of Connecticut, 1941-1943.
Died: May 3, 1968 at West Hartford, Connecticut.
The election of Robert Hurley marked the first time that Connecticut placed a Catholic into the office of governor. It had taken just over 300 years for the state's political process to move to the point where it would accept a non-Protestant for this position. Hurley grew up in Bridgeport and attended Lehigh University where he was a top athlete. His education was disrupted by his service with the U.S. Navy in World War I. After the war he played professional football and semi-professional baseball before working with his father in the construction and engineering business. Later he owned his own company. He was married to Evelyn Hedberg and they had three children.
Hurley was named director of Fairfield County's Work Project Administration in 1935 and two years later he became Connecticut's first Public Works commissioner. An advocate of the New Deal, Hurley defeated Wilbur Cross at the 1940 Democratic state convention and went on to wrest the governor's position from incumbent, Raymond Baldwin. During his one term he was able to introduce some reform programs to help workers and the unemployed. He also helped Connecticut's rural areas receive electricity. As the United States became more involved with World War II, Hurley pushed the state to be prepared for the conflict even though this was done at the expense of New Deal programs. As a war governor he was able to obtain assurances from labor and industry that strikes would not occur. Production problems at home and the rationing of consumer products led some voters to disapprove of his administration. Yet, most of the people in Connecticut were employed and prosperity had been realized.
Hurley sought to be reelected in 1942, but he lost to former governor, Raymond Baldwin. He won his party's nomination in 1944, but again lost to Baldwin. Hurley then retired from politics and this allowed the Democratic Party, which had split into factions, to become unified two years later under its new party chairman, John Bailey. Hurley became an officer in a company in Rhode Island, but he lived in West Hartford for 30 years. He is buried in the town's Fairview Cemetery. His house still stands and is privately owned.
Bibliography
Congressional Quarterly's Guide to United States Elections. Washington, D.C.: Congressional Quarterly, 1994 [CSL call number GIS Ref JK 1967 .C662 1994.
Glashan, Roy R. American Governors and Gubernatorial Elections, 1775-1975. Stillwater, Minn.: Croixside Press, 1975 [CSL call number JK 2447 .G53 1975].
Sobel, Robert and John Raimo. Biographical Directory of the Governors of the United States, 1789-1978. Westport, Conn.: Meckler Books, 1978 [CSL call number GIS Ref E 176 .B573].
Van Dusen, Albert E. Connecticut. New York: Random House, 1961. [CSL call number HistRef F 94 .V3].
Scope and Content
Gov. Robert A. Hurley's records are correspondence and subject files related to state agencies, commissions, legislative bills, and appointments among other topics.
Arrangement
Series 1. Correspondence.
Series 2. Subject Files.
Series 3. Charges against William J. Cox, Highway Commissioner.
Related Material
None.
Index Terms
Persons:
Hurley, Robert Augustine, 1895-
Subjects:
Hurley, Robert Augustine, 1895- -- Archives; Connecticut. Office of the Governor -- Archives; Connecticut -- History -- Sources; Connecticut -- Politics and government -- 1865-1950 -- Sources; Governors -- Connecticut -- Archives
Document Types:
Correspondence; Records
Restrictions on Access
These records are stored at an off-site facility and therefore may not be available on a same-day basis.
See the policy.
Container List
- Series 1. Correspondence, T001237
  - General A, B, D, L, M, P, Q, S, T, U, V, W (Box 435)
- Series 2. Subject Files, T001237
  - Adjutant General (Armory) (Box 436)
  - Adjutant General - Legislation (Suggested) (Box 436)
  - Aeronautic Department (Box 436)
  - Aeronautical Development Commission (Box 436)
  - Agriculture, Department of (Box 436)
  - Agriculture, Establishing Department of – (Leg[islation]) (Box 436)
  - American Legion, Dept. of Conn. (Box 436)
  - Appointments (By Gov[ernor]) (Box 436)
  - Athletic Commission (Box 436)
  - Attorney General (Box 436)
  - Auditors of Public Accounts (Box 436)
  - Banking Department (Box 436)
  - Banking – Leg[islation] (Box 436)
  - Bar Association, State of Conn. (Box 436)
  - Barber Examiners, Board of (Box 436)
  - Bills – Labor (Leg[islation]) Vetoed (Box 436)
  - Bills – (List) (Box 436)
  - Bills – (List - Introduced, 1/29, 30 and 31/41) (Box 436)
  - Bills – (“Representative Town meeting Bill of Trumbull”) Vetoed (Leg[islation]) (Box 436)
  - Bills - Vetoed (Box 436)
  - Boards and Commissions (Box 436)
  - Brasher Paintings (Box 436)
  - Bridge (Box 436)
  - Bridgeport, City of (Box 436)
  - Building Fund, Unappropriated Surplus of the (Box 436)
  - Cheshire Academy (Box 436)
  - Cheshire Academy Drive (Box 436)
  - Children in Democracy - (Governor’s Committee of the White House Conference) (Box 436)
  - Coast Guard – (Avery Point Site) (Box 436)
  - Complimentary Letters (Box 436)
  - Comptroller (Box 436)
  - Contingent Fund (Gov[ernor]) (Box 436)
  - Council of State Governments, The (Box 436)
  - County Jails (Box 436)
  - Crime (Box 436)
  - Dairy and Food Commission (Box 436)
  - Danbury Hatters (Box 436)
  - Defense (Box 436)
  - Defense - Air Corps Commissions (Box 436)
  - Defense - Airports (Box 436)
  - Defense - Aluminum (Box 436)
  - Defense – ATCA [Air Training Corps of America. Pre-flight Instruction] (Box 436)
  - Defense – Aviation (Box 436)
  - Defense – Bomber Plane (Box 436)
  - Defense – Bonds (Box 436)
  - Defense – Camp Blanding (Box 436)
  - Defense – Camp Edwards and Fort Terry (Box 436)
  - Defense – Car Freezing (Box 436)
  - Defense – Casualties (Box 436)
  - Defense – Coal (Box 436)
  - Defense – Commission - Legislation (Box 436)
  - Defense – Committee, Joint Executive (Box 436)
  - Defense – Committee to Defend America by Aiding the Allies (Box 436)
  - Defense – Conn. War Ind[ustries] Com[mission] (Box 437)
  - Defense – Conservation (Box 437)
  - Defense – Education (Box 437)
  - Defense – Evacuation (Box 437)
  - Defense – Finance (Box 437)
  - Defense – Fishing Coordination (Box 437)
  - Defense – Fuel Oil (Box 437)
  - Defense – Gas (Box 437)
  - Defense – Guards for Plant Protection (Box 437)
  - Defense – Health and Welfare (Box 437)
  - Defense – Housing – Emergency Committee (Box 437)
  - Defense – Job Discrimination Committee [Report of Conference and Correspondence] (Box 437)
  - Defense – Labor [4 folders] (Box 437)
  - Defense – Labor Compact (Box 438)
  - Defense – Labor Disputes (Box 438)
  - Defense – Legal Aid (Box 438)
  - Defense – Manpower (Box 438)
  - Defense – Merritt Parkway (Box 438)
  - Defense – Migratory Workers (Box 438)
  - Defense – Military Coordinator (Box 438)
  - Defense – Negroes [Correspondence with Harold R. Peters, New Haven, 1942] (Box 438)
  - Defense – (Post-War) (Box 438)
  - Defense – Precautions (Box 438)
  - Defense – Price Administration (Box 438)
  - Defense – Priorities on Materials (Box 438)
  - Defense – Production Clinic (Box 438)
  - Defense – Rent Control (Box 438)
  - Defense – Sabotage - 5th Column Activities, etc. (Box 438)
  - Defense – Salvage (Box 438)
  - Defense –Selective Service – Negroes [Governor Hurley favors drafting blacks.] (Box 438)
  - Defense – Selective Service [3 folders] (Box 438)
  - Defense – Soldiers’ Recreation System (Box 439)
  - Defense – Taxation (Box 439)
  - Defense – Tire Rationing (Box 439)
  - Defense – United Service Organization (Box 439)
  - Development Commission (Box 439)
  - Development Commission – Legislation (Suggested) (Box 439)
  - Domestic Animals Commission (Box 439)
  - Eastern States Exposition (Box 439)
  - Education, Department of (Box 439)
  - Edwards, General – Memorial (Box 439)
  - Employment Serv[ice] (Box 439)
  - Extradition (Box 439)
  - Finance and Control, Dept. of (Administrative Division) (Box 439)
  - Finance and Control, Dept. of (Budget Division) (Box 439)
  - Finance and Control, Dept. of (Personnel Division) (Box 439)
  - Finance and Control, Dept. of (Purchasing Division) (Box 439)
  - Fire and Safety Hazards (Box 439)
  - Fish and Game, State Board of (Box 439)
  - Flood Control (Box 439)
  - Foreign Consuls in U. S. A. (Box 439)
  - Forestry Department (Box 439)
  - General Assembly, Messages to (Box 439)
  - General Assembly, Special Session, October 19, 1942 (Box 439)
  - Geological and Natural History Survey, Connecticut (Box 439)
  - Governor (Car) (Box 439)
  - Governors’ Conference (Box 439)
  - Governor’s Foot Guards, 1st & 2nd Companies (Hartford & New Haven) (Box 439)
  - Governor’s Staff (Box 439)
  - Groton Ironworks (Box 439)
  - Group Life Insurance (Box 439)
  - Health and Safety Commission (Box 439)
  - Health Department (Box 439)
  - Highway and Bridges (Box 439)
  - Highway Department (Box 439)
  - Highway Dept. – (Carstens) (Box 439)
  - Highway Dept. – (Collier) (Box 439)
  - Highway Dept. – (Cox-Special) (Box 439)
  - Highway Dept. Funds (Box 439)
  - Highway Dept. – Legislation (Suggested) (Box 439)
  - House Bills (Box 439)
  - Housing - (Leg[islation]) (Box 439)
  - Institutions – Conn. Reformatory (Box 439)
  - Institutions – Conn. State Farm for Women - Niantic (Box 439)
  - Institutions – Conn. State Hospital (Box 439)
  - Institutions – Conn. State Prison (Box 439)
  - Institutions – Fairfield State Hospital (Box 440)
  - Institutions – Mansfield Training School (Box 440)
  - Institutions – Norwich State Hospital (Box 440)
  - Institutions – Southbury Training School (Box 440)
  - Institutions – State Legislation - Miscellaneous (Box 440)
  - Insurance Department (Box 440)
  - Interceptor Command (Box 440)
  - Juvenile Courts (Leg[islation]) (Box 440)
  - Labor (Box 440)
  - Labor and Factory Inspection (Box 440)
  - Labor and Factory Inspection (Unemployment Compensation Division) (Box 440)
  - Legal Opinions (Attorney General) (Box 440)
  - Legislative Bills (Box 440)
  - Library and Supreme Court Bldg., State (Box 440)
  - Liquor Control – Leg[islation] (Box 440)
  - Maritime Academy, (Mystic) (Box 440)
  - Marriages – (Requests for Authorization) (Box 440)
  - Merit System Legislation 1941 (Box 440)
  - Merritt Parkway Commission (Box 440)
  - Milk Administration (Box 440)
  - Milk Control (Leg[islation]) (Box 440)
  - Motor Vehicle Department (Box 440)
  - Motor Vehicle Dept. - Legislation (Box 440)
  - National Guard - Connecticut (Box 440)
  - Navy Day (Box 440)
  - Negro Employment Problem (Box 440)
  - New Haven Fire (Box 440)
  - New Haven Harbor Development (Box 440)
  - Nominations by Governor to G. A. [General Assembly] (Box 440)
  - N.Y.A. [National Youth Administration] – (Ceremonies, Feb. 27, 1942) (Box 440)
  - Offers of Reward (Box 440)
  - Pardons, State Board of (Box 440)
  - Park Department (Box 440)
  - Personnel Salary Increases (Box 440)
  - Petitions (Box 440)
  - Police Department (Box 440)
  - Prison (Leg[islation]) (Box 440)
  - Proclamations (Box 440)
  - Propaganda Leg[islation] (Box 440)
  - Public Utilities Commission (Box 440)
  - Public Utilities Legislation (Box 440)
  - Public Welfare Department (Administrative Div[ision]) (Box 440)
  - Public Welfare Department (Public Welfare Council) (Box 440)
  - Public Works Department (Box 440)
  - Public Works Reserve (Box 440)
  - Publicity - Movie (Box 440)
  - Publicity - New Releases (Box 440)
  - Publicity - Radio Broadcasts (Box 440)
  - Quartermaster General (Box 440)
  - Reapportionment (Box 440)
  - Resignations (Box 440)
  - Resolutions (Box 440)
  - Retirement Commission (Box 441)
  - Retirement of State Employees – Leg[islation] (Box 441)
  - Savings Bank Insurance – Trustees (Box 441)
  - Saxon, O. Glenn (Box 441)
  - Selective Service – Olson Case (Box 441)
  - Senate Bills (Box 441)
  - Sherwood Island (Box 441)
  - Soil Conservation – Leg[islation] (Box 441)
  - Soldiers’, Sailors’ and Marines’ Fund (Box 441)
  - Stamford, City of (Box 441)
  - State Guard - Connecticut (Box 441)
  - Statements [3 folders] (Box 441)
  - Statute Revision Department (Box 441)
  - Steamship Terminals Commission (Box 441)
  - Strubing Case (Box 441)
  - (Talbot vs. Fair - Chester Oil Co., Inc.) (Box 441)
  - Tax, Commission to Study (Temp[orary]) – (Leg[islation]) (Box 441)
  - Tax Department (Administrative Div[ision]) (Box 441)
  - Taxes (Box 441)
  - Traffic and Safety (Box 441)
  - Treasury Department (Box 441)
  - Tuberculosis Commission (Box 441)
  - Unemployment Compensation – (Federalization) (Box 441)
  - Unemployment Compensation – (Leg[islation]) (Box 441)
  - Uniformity of Legislation in U.S., Conn. Commission for (Box 441)
  - University of Connecticut (Box 441)
  - University of Connecticut (Appropriation for R. O. T. C. facilities) (Box 441)
  - Veterans’ Home Commission (Box 441)
  - Volunteer Service – Conn. St[ate] Guard (Box 441)
  - Water Commission (Box 441)
  - Waters, Committee on New England (Box 441)
  - Works Progress Admin[istration] - Conn. (Box 441)
- Series 3. Charges against William J. Cox, Highway Commissioner, 1942; 1993-149
  - Volumes 1-7 (Box 1)
  - Volumes 8-9 (Box 2)